<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
   [<!ENTITY appname          "Viking">]
>

<section id="EditViewMenu"><title>Edit and View Menus</title>

<section><title>Standard Edit Entries</title>
<para>
  Besides the standard edit entries (Cut, Copy, Paste, Delete) that operate on the currently selected item,
  there is also the <guilabel>Delete All</guilabel> which removes <emphasis>ALL</emphasis> layers
  (including the automatically created Default Map).
</para>
</section><!-- End Standard Edit Entries-->

<section><title>Map/Position Edit Entries</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Copy Center Location</guilabel></term>
<listitem>
  <para>This will copy the current center of the viewport as coordinate lat/lon pair in plain text, such that it can be then be pasted into other applications.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Flush Map Memory Cache</guilabel></term>
<listitem>
  <para>This will empty the in memory map cache, hence it should reduce the amount of memory that &appname; is using.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Set Default Location</guilabel></term>
<listitem>
  <para>This will set the Default Location (AKA the Home Location) to current center position of the viewport.</para>
  <para>See <xref linkend="GoHome"/>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section><!-- End Map/Position Edit Entries-->

<section><title>&appname; Configuration Edit Entries</title>
<para>
  Allows access to &appname; <xref linkend="prefs"/>.
</para>
<para>
  Allows access to the <xref linkend="Layers"/> defaults.
  When creating a new layer it will start with the default values as specified here.
</para>
<para>
  Access to show the messages that are being suppressed and the ability to reset back to the default of no messages being suppressed.
  Some warning style messages can be selected to be ignored, since if they repeatedly come up in your work flow they could otherwise become tiresome.
</para>
</section><!-- End Configuration Edit Entries-->


<section><title>Mode View Entries</title>
<para>
  Allows selection of the <xref linkend="projection"/> mode.
</para>
</section><!-- End Mode View Entries-->

<section><title>Go to View Entries</title>
<para>
  Offers a selection of methods to jump to a position in the world.
</para>
<para>
  The Go to Lat/Lon dialog method allows manually specifying the coordinates to move to.
  <note>
    <para>
      The latitude entry (although a spin button) can accept any text and will be attempted to be used as a <xref linkend="LatLonInput"/>.
    </para>
  </note>
</para>
<para>
  Additionally there is method to move the calendar view to todays date.
</para>
</section><!-- End Go to View Entries-->

<section><title>Colour View Entries</title>
<para>
  These entries allow setting the default background colour (i.e. when there are no maps) and the highlight colour for selected tracks and waypoints.
</para>
</section><!-- End Colour View Entries-->

<section><title>Zoom View Entries</title>
<para>
  Offers a selection of methods to zoom the viewport, including not only <guilabel>In</guilabel> and <guilabel>Out</guilabel> but also to any specific level.
</para>
</section><!-- End Zoom View Entries-->

<section><title>Show View Entries</title>
<para>
  Offers a selection of methods to control visibility of various screen elements.
  Most of these can also be accessed via <xref linkend="shortcut_keys"/>.
</para>
</section><!-- End Show View Entries-->

<section><title>Dialog View Entries</title>
<para>
  Offers alternative access to additional informational dialogs. Otherwise these can be accessed from the <xref linkend="Statusbar"/>.
</para>
</section><!-- End Dialog View Entries-->

</section><!-- End Edit/View -->
